Aymar Embury II Papers
Aymar Embury II Papers
1902-1965
Embury, Aymar, 1880-1966
35 linear ft.
Papers of the American architect. Died 1966. Architectural drawings and designs, photographs and slides, material relating to bridge design, articles by and about Embury.
148963
Biographical History
Aymar Embury II (1880-1966) was an American architect.
Born in New York City, Embury graduated from Princeton University in 1900 with a bachelor's degree in engineering. He earned a master's degree the same subject in 1901, and began practicing architecture in New York City that same year. Embury taught architecture at Princeton while also working for various firms in New York City, including Cass Gilbert, George B. Post, Howells & Stokes, and Palmer and Hornbostel. During the First World War he served as a captain with the 40th Engineers of the United States Army, and designed the Distinguished Service Cross and the Distinguished Service Medal (Army).
Embury's specialties were college buildings, urban and country houses, hotels, library buildings, banks, clubs and community buildings. He was the architect for college buildings at Princeton University, Kalamazoo College, and Hofstra College and created two housing developments. His most significant efforts, however, were in connection with Parks Commissioner Robert Moses, with whom he worked as architect and supervisor of a design and construction team that executed more than six hundred projects for the city of New York, including the Triborough Bridge, the Lincoln Tunnel, the Henry Hudson Memorial Bridge, the Whitestone Bridge, the Rainbow Bridge, the Jamaica Bay Bridge and The Port of New York Authority Terminal Building. Embury was also the architect for the New York City and Argentine Pavilions at the 1939 World's Fair held in New York City.
Embury was a member of the President's Advisory Committee on Architecture from 1934-1943. He was also a member of the American Society of Civil Engineers and the New York Society of Architects. Mr. Embury wrote a number of books, including 100 Country Houses (1901), The Dutch Colonial House (1911), Country Houses (1914), Early American Churches (1914), The Liveable House (1917), and The Esthetics of Engineering Construction (1943).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Aymar Embury II Papers contains writings, photographs, prints, sketches, shop drawings, and published material. Material was received in two separate accessions (1967 and 1980), which have been integrated.
Correspondence contains one incoming and one outgoing piece of correspondence between Evans Kerrigan and Embury.
Memorabilia consists of a photographic portrait of Embury, a Christmas drawing, lithographs of bridges designed by Embury and various scrapbooks of his work, including bridges, churches, country clubs, residences, etc..
The Projects by Embury series contains contract documents, drawings and photographs for buildings designed by Embury or for which he served as a consulting architect.
Projects by other architects includes photographs and information on buildings not constructed by Embury. It also includes stock designs for post offices for the President's Advisory Committee on Architecture. Embury served as the Chairman of this committee. Projects designed by other architects under his leadership can be found here. Post offices designed by Embury for this committee are found under Projects by Embury.
Writings by Embury consists of manuscripts and published versions of articles on architecture, engineering, design and a limited number of short stories and autobiographical writings by Embury.
Writings on Embury includes articles in various trade journals and pamphlets on his work.
Writings on other architects includes articles on architectural plates and on William Jensen, an employee of Embury's office.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically, by type where relevant, and then by title. Because the scrapbooks contain materials related to several projects, they have been placed in Memorabilia rather than Projects by Embury. Stock post office designs produced under the aegis of the President's Committee on Architecture, for which Embury served as chairman, have been divided between two series, Projects by Embury and Projects by other architects.
Separated Material
A parallel of architecture by Jean-Louis-Nicolas Durand was transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Embury, Aymar, 1880-1966.; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984.; Embury, Edward Coe.; Chrystie, Edward F.; Jensen, William.; Klauder, Charles A.; Rowe, J. Richard.; Embury and Lucas.; Amann and Whitney.; Sigmond and Farkas.; Architects -- United States.; Architectural design.; Architecture -- Designs and plans.; Architectural drawing -- 20th century -- United States.; Architectural firms.; Architecture -- New York (State); Architecture -- United States.; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Architecture, American.; Bridges -- Design and construction.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Essays.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Kerrigan, Evans E., 1964 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Portrait of Embury (Box 1)
  - Merry Christmas drawing, ink on tracing paper drawing (Tube 950)
  - Lithographs of drawings of bridges by J. Richard Rowe, lithographs (some duplicates) including one of the Triborough Bridge tower lift span over the Harlem River and the anchorage of the George Washington Bridge; 13 items (Map-case 129)
    See also the Bridges scrapbooks, the Triborough bridge and the George Washington bridge for photographs of these structures.
  - Scrapbooks
    - 70th and 71st Street houses (New York, New York), exterior and interior photographs labeled Rothschild, Charles McVeigh and Bernard (Oversize 1)
    - Bridges, contains photographs of various bridges designed by Embury including the Triborough Bridge; Marine Parkway Bridge; Lincoln Tunnel; George Washington Bridge anchorage; Henry Hudson bridge; and Croton Lake bridge; 2 scrapbooks (Oversize 7)
      See also the Triborough bridge, the Marine Parkway bridge, the Lincoln Tunnel, and the George Washington bridge for more photographs of these structures.
    - Churches, contains photographs of the Chapel in Watch Hill, RI; the First Congregational Church (Kalamazoo, Michigan); and the First Congregational Church (Springfield, VT) (Oversize 5)
      See also the First Congregational church, Kalamazoo and the First Congregational church, Springfield for more photographs of these churches.
    - Country clubs, contains photographs of the Charlotte Country Club and the Mountain Brook Country Club (Oversize 6)
      See also the Charlotte Country Club and the Mountain Brook Country Club for more photographs of this structure.
    - Kalamazoo, MI buildings, contains photographs of the First Congregational Church and Kalamazoo College buildings, etc. (Oversize 6)
      See also the First Congregational church, Kalamazoo and Kalamazoo College for more photographs of these buildings.
    - Mountain Brook Country Club (Birmingham, Alabama), contains interior and exterior photographs (Oversize 6)
      See also the Mountain Brook Country Club for more photographs of this structure.
    - New York parks buildings, contains photographs of buildings including Sunset Park; Municipal Stadium (Randall's Island); Orchard Beach Bath House (Pelham Bay Park); Colonial Park Play Center; Arsenal; Central Park Zoo (Oversize 5)
    - Oltman residence (Alpine, New York), contains interior and exterior photographs (Oversize 8)
      See also Oltman residence for more photographs of this house.
    - Princeton Club of New York (New York, New York), contains interior and exterior photographs (Oversize 6)
      See also the Princeton Club for more photographs of this club.
    - Residences, contains photographs of interior of Luther Blake residence (Bernardsville, New Jersey); interior of Richard Bernhard residence; interior of Charles McVeigh residence; exterior and interior of Arthur Lehman residence (New York, New York) (Oversize 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Oversize 8)
      photographs of Aqueduct Race Track (Queens, New York); Congregational Church (Winnetka, Illinois); Dennison (Saddle River); Gas Station (Randall's Island, New York); Hotel Merida (Merida, Mexico); Jamaica Race Track (Queens, New York); Metropolitan Museum (New York, New York); Port Authority Building (New York, New York); Post Office (Lakewood, New Jersey); Toll and Administration Building (Marine Parkway); World's Fair, New York City Building (Queens, New York); includes drawing of farm building on the estate of Mr. and Mrs. Randolph Catlin (Charlottesville, VA)
      See also the Catlin estate, Congregational church (Winnetka), Hotel Merida, the Marine Parkway bridge, Metropolitan Museum, addition, and the World's Fair for more photographs of these buildings.
- Projects by Embury
  - Adams residence (East Hampton, New York), Mrs. John Cranford Adams (client)
    - Contract documents, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Drawings, 1958; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 18 items (Tube 934)
  - Arthur residence (Lloyd Harbor, Huntington, Long Island, New York), Mr. and Mrs. Donald Arthur, Jr. (client); Embury and Lucas (architects); Edward Coe Embury (architect); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, 1950; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 22 items (Tube 932)
    - Drawings, 1950; graphite on tracing paper design development drawings; 45 items (Tube 933)
  - Arthur residence, addition (Lloyd Harbor, Huntington, Long Island, New York)
    - Drawings, 1962; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 8 items (Tube 932)
  - Astor residence (Newport, RI), Vincent Astor (client)
    - Drawings, graphite sketch on back of envelope (Oversize 1)
    - Photographs, exterior and grounds (12); interiors (2); negatives (6); 20 items (Box 1)
  - Bascule bridge over Flushing river (Queens, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper drawing (1); reproductions of drawings (4); 5 items (Oversize 4)
  - Battery-Brooklyn bridge and Battery Park (Brooklyn, New York)
    - Photographs, bridge (7); model (2); photographs of drawings (5); 14 items (Box 1)
  - Battery Park (Brooklyn, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite drawing on tracing paper mounted on board showing suggested treatment of main axis (Oversize 10)
  - Bellport Memorial Library (Bellport, Long Island, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior; 9 items (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1923; exterior (Oversize 1)
  - Betts residence (Darien, CT)
    - Photographs, 1938; exterior; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Boyd residence (Southern Pines, North Carolina), James Boyd (client)
    - Photographs, 1922; exterior (17); interior (2); photographs, possibly of an existing structure (4); 23 items (Box 1)
  - Bridge over Passaic river (Newark, New Jersey)
    - Drawings, reproductions of drawings; 4 items (Oversize 4)
  - Bronx Zoo (Bronx, New York)
    - Crotona toll house, Harrison, Fouilhoux and Abramovitz (architects); Aymar Embury II (associated architect)
      - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper (1); negative photostat of plan, elevation and perspective (1); 2 items (Oversize 10)
    - Great apes house
      - Photographs, 1950; exterior; 17 items (Box 1)
    - Penguin house
      - Photographs, 1950; interior (17); sign (1); 18 items (Box 1)
    - South approach to bridge over Bronx river
      - Drawings, graphite on board perspective of bridge (Oversize 9)
  - Brookhaven library (Brookhaven, Long Island, New York)
    - Drawings, 1925; blueprint (1); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (9); 10 items (Tube 934)
  - Brooklyn bridge, proposed alterations (Brooklyn, New York)
    - Photographs, photographs of drawings; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn war memorial (Brooklyn, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper mounted on board; 2 items (Oversize 10)
  - Bulova watch factory (Queens, New York), Alexander D. Crosett & Associates (architects); Aymer Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Advertisement, February 1954; featured in Fortune Magazine (Oversize 1)
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 1)
  - Cady residence (Southern Pines, North Carolina), Dr. E. E. Cady (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (7); interior (1); 8 items (Box 1)
  - Captree toll control
    - Drawings, negative photostat of perspective drawing (Oversize 9)
  - Catlin estate, farm buildings (Charlottesville, VA), Mr. and Mrs. Randolph Catlin (client)
    See also Miscellaneous scrapbook for more photographs of this building.
    - Drawings, graphite drawings of perspective, plans and elevation on board (Oversize 4)
  - Central Park band stand (New York, New York)
    - Drawings, positive photostat of rendering (Oversize 9)
  - Chapel (Watch Hill, RI)
    - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Charlotte Country Club (Charlotte, North Carolina)
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 1)
      See also Country club scrapbook for more photographs of this building.
  - Charlotte Country Club, golf shop (Charlotte, North Carolina)
    - Drawings, working drawings, graphite on tracing paper; 7 items (Tube 934)
  - Chauncey residence (East Hampton, Long Island, New York), A. Wallace Chauncey (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (7); interior (9); also includes a scrapbook, "Our Place" by Emma Romeyn; 16 items (Box 1)
  - Church of Saint James the Less (Scarsdale, New York)
    - Drawings, perspective (Oversize 9)
  - Coe residence (Englewood, New Jersey), E. P. Coe (client); first house designed by Embury circa 1902 according to note on wrapping for drawings
    - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper working drawings (21); ink on linen working drawings (14); 35 items (Tube 936)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); interior (3); 4 items (Oversize 1)
    - Specifications (Box 1)
  - Collins residence (Princeton, New Jersey), V. Lansing Collins (client)
    - Specifications (Box 1)
  - Congregational church (Scarsdale, New York)
    - Drawings, positive photostat of watercolor rendering (Oversize 9)
  - Davison residence (Princeton, New Jersey), C. Herbert Davison (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (5); interior (2); 7 items (Box 1)
  - Donnell Free Circulating Library and reading room (New York, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); interior (7); 8 items (Box 1)
  - Dull residence (Southern Pines, North Carolina), Mrs. A. P. L. Dull (client)
    - Photographs, August 1921; exterior (28); interior (6); 34 items (Box 1)
  - DuPont Country Club (Wilmington, Delaware)
    - Drawings, reproductions of perspective drawings; 4 items (Oversize 1)
    - Drawings, 1946-1948; graphite on linen working drawings (10); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (41); 51 items (Tube 937)
    - Drawings, 1946-1948; graphite on tracing paper drawings; mix of design development and working drawings; 110 items (Tube 938)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); negative photostat of exterior (1); 2 items (Box 1)
  - East Hampton library (East Hampton, Long Island, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior and grounds (12); 5 photographs of interior (5); negative photostat of drawing (1); 18 items (Box 1)
    - Photographs, exterior (3); interior (2); 5 items (Oversize 1)
  - Embury residence (Englewood, New Jersey), Aymar Embury II (client)
    - Specifications (Box 1)
  - Fay residence (Dougan Hills, Staten Island, New York), C. J. Fay (client)
    - Photographs, exterior; 7 items (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior; 1 has reproductions of plans attached; 6 items (Oversize 1)
  - First Congregational church (Kalamazoo, Michigan)
    See also Churches scrapbook and Kalamazoo scrapbook for more photographs of this church.
    - Photographs, exterior (13); negative photostat of exterior (1); interior (13); negative photostat of interior (1); construction photographs (8); and photographs of plans (2); 2 folders, 38 items (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior (Oversize 1)
  - First Congregational church (Springfield, VT)
    See also Churches scrapbook for more photographs of this church.
    - Photographs, 1927; exterior (15); interior (18); 33 items (Box 2)
  - First Presbyterian church (Freeport, Long Island, New York)
    - Drawings, 1944; sepia diazo print (Tube 935)
  - Garden State Parkway buildings (NJ)
    - Drawings, 1953; graphite on board perspectives; 6 items (Oversize 10)
  - Gaylord residence (Rodsford, Illinois), Robert M. Gaylord (client)
    - Drawings, negative photostat of exterior perspective (Oversize 1)
    - Drawings, 1949-1952; graphite on tracing paper drawings; mix of design development and working drawings; 48 items (Tube 943)
    - Drawings, 1949-1952; graphite on tracing paper drawings; mix of design development and working drawings; 84 items (Tube 944)
    - Photographs, exterior; 6 items (Box 2)
  - Gaylord residence, addition (Rodsford, Illinois), Edward Coe Embury (architect); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, 1958; graphite on tracing paper working drawings (14); sepia diazo print working drawings (1); 15 items (Tube 944)
    - Specifications, 1958 (Box 2)
  - George Washington bridge (New York, New York)
    See also Bridges scrapbooks and Lithographs of Bridges for more images of this structure.
    - Drawings, reproductions of drawings (3); photostat of article layout (1); 4 items (Oversize 4)
  - Golf house, Edward Coe Embury (architect); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, 1956; graphite on tracing paper working drawing (1); graphite on paper design development drawing (1); 2 items (Tube 950)
  - Greek Orthodox church
    - Drawings, positive (1) and negative (1) photostat of watercolor rendering; 2 items (Oversize 9)
  - Greyhound bus terminal
    - Drawings, reproduction of drawing (Oversize 9)
  - Guild Hall (East Hampton, Long Island, New York)
    - Photographs, exterior (3); interior (5); 8 items (Box 2)
    - Drawings, 1931; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 42 items (Tube 928)
    - Drawings, 1931; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; very large; 10 items (Tube 929)
    - Drawings, 1931; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; very large; 8 items (Tube 930)
    - Drawings, 1930-1931; ink on linen working drawings (4); graphite on linen working drawings (3); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (26); 33 items (Tube 931)
  - Haas residence ( Mt. Kisco, New York), George Haas (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 2)
  - Haggerty residence (Remsenburg, Long Island, New York), Joseph J. Haggerty (client)
    - Drawings, envelope with sketch (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior; 3 items (Box 2)
  - Harbor Acres (Port Washington, Long Island, New York)
    - Gate lodge
      - Drawings, 1926; color prints of drawing; 2 items (Oversize 1)
      - Photographs, 1926; exterior (6); interior (1); 7 items (Oversize 1)
    - Signs
      - Drawings, graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 10 items (Tube 935)
  - Harvard Business School, competition (Cambridge, MA)
    - Drawings, positive photostats of drawings of dining halls and library; 2 items (Oversize 9)
    - Photographs, photographs of drawings; 7 items (Box 2)
  - Hastings residence, alterations (68 E. 54th Street, New York, New York), Mrs. George Hastings (clients)
    - Specifications (Box 2)
  - Highland Pines Inn (Southern Pines, North Carolina)
    - Drawings, printed plan (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior (26); interior (6); photograph of drawing (1); postcards (7); 40 items (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior (8); interior (2); 10 items (Oversize 1)
  - Highway and railway bridges (Summit, Delaware)
    - Drawings, drawings (3); reproductions of drawings (19); 22 items (Oversize 4)
    - Photographs, photograph of bridge (Oversize 4)
  - Hillsdale College, chapel (Hillsdale, Michigan)
    - Drawings, negative photostat of plan (Box 2)
  - Hitchcock Memorial Presbyterian church (Scarsdale, New York), Embury and Lucas (architects); Aymar Embury II (consulting architect)
    - Drawings, graphite on board drawings; 3 items (Map-case 128)
  - Hofstra College (Hempstead, Long Island, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite drawings on tracing paper or board (4) and positive photostats of drawings (7); 11 items; 2 folders (Oversize 10)
    - Photographs, photographs of college buildings and grounds; 36 items (Box 2)
  - Hope Valley Country Club (Hope Valley, North Carolina)
    - Photographs, exterior (12); interior (3); photograph of plan (1); 16 items (Box 2)
  - Hotel Merida (Yucatan, Mexico), "Arturo Ponce" written in parentheses under the project name on the wrapping for the drawings
    See also Miscellaneous scrapbook for more photographs of this hotel.
    - Drawings, plans on board; 2 items (Oversize 9)
    - Drawings, 1941; 1946,; 1952; graphite on drawing paper design development drawings (5); graphite on tracing paper working drawings (62); diazo print working drawings (2); 69 items (Tube 948)
  - Hughes residence (Bedford Hills, New York)
    - Drawings, plans mounted on board; 2 items (Oversize 1)
    - Photographs, exterior (9); interiors (26); postcards (3); 38 items (Box 2)
    - Photographs, exterior (3); interiors (4); 7 items (Oversize 1)
  - John Street church (New York, New York)
    - Drawings, graphite drawing on board (1); conte crayon drawings on tracing paper mounted on board (3); graphite sketch on paper (1); photostats of plans (3); 8 items (Oversize 9)
    - Photographs, exterior (1); photostats of interior (2); photostats of exterior (5); 8 items (Oversize 9)
  - Johnson residence (Englewood, New Jersey), Leonard Johnson (client)
    - Photographs, exterior; 11 items (Box 3)
    - Photographs, exterior (14); interior (4); 18 items (Oversize 2)
  - Johnson, Drake and Piper
    - Photographs, exterior (Box 3)
  - Junior high school, No. 77 (Brooklyn, New York)
    - Drawings, watercolor of typical window bay (1); negative photostats of perspectives, plans, window, etc. (8); transparent film of perspective (1); 10 items; 2 folders (Oversize 9)
  - Kalamazoo Civic Auditorium (Kalamazoo, Michigan)
    - Brochure (Box 3)
    - Drawings, 1930; graphite on tracing paper working drawings; 25 items (Tube 935)
    - Photographs, exterior (3); interior (13); negative transparencies of exterior (4); negative transparencies of interior (10); 30 items (Box 3)
  - Kalamazoo College (Kalamazoo, Michigan)
    See also Kalamazoo scrapbook for more photographs of these buildings.
    - Bowen Hall
      - Drawings, 1965; diazo print working drawings (5); graphite on tracing paper design development drawing (1); 6 items (Tube 950)
    - New girl's dormitories, proposed scheme
      - Drawings, 1945-1946; graphite on tracing paper design development drawings (8); blueprint working drawing (1); photostats of perspective drawings (2); 11 items (Tube 947)
    - Stetson Chapel
      - Photographs, exterior; 2 items (Box 3)
  - King Jagielo monument (Central Park, New York, New York)
    - Drawings, 1945; negative photostat of plan and elevation (Oversize 9)
  - King residence (Irvington-on-Hudson, New York), F. P. King (client)
    - Photographs, exterior (11); exterior photograph cut from an unknown publication (1); 12 items (Box 3)
    - Photographs, exterior; 7 (Oversize 2)
  - Knickerbocker Country Club (Tenafly, New Jersey)
    - Photographs, exterior (21); interior (15); 36 items (Box 3)
  - Lincoln Tunnel
    See also Bridges scrapbooks for more photographs of this structure.
    - Drawings, reproductions of drawings; 8 items (Oversize 4)